{"tossups": [{"question": "Description acceptable. This event was thought to have occurred in retaliation for the bombing of the perpetrator\u2019s Tunisian headquarters in Operation Wooden Leg. Muhammad Zaidan organized this event, which involved the redirection of a vessel to Tartus, Syria. A John Adams opera focusing on this event opens with two choruses of exiles and is named after its only casualty, the 69-year old Leon Klinghoffer. For ten points, name this 1985 event in which members of the Palestine Liberation Front hijacked an Italian passenger liner.", "answer": "<b> hijack</b>ing of the MS<b> Achille Lauro</b> (accept equivalents for<b> hijack</b>ing, like<b> take over</b>; accept descriptions of a<b> terrorist attack on the Achille Lauro</b>; prompt on descriptions of the death of (Leon) Klinghoffer before \u201cKlinghoffer\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At the start of this battle, Herwarth von Bittenfeld held a defensive position on the Bystrice River. The cutting of telegraph lines before this battle delayed the arrival of Frederick III\u2019s 2nd Army. A month after this battle, the winners pushed for lenient surrender terms in the Peace of Prague and the North German Confederation was formed without this battle\u2019s loser, which formed a dual monarchy with Hungary a year later. For ten points, name this decisive victory for the elder Helmuth von Moltke during the Seven Weeks War in which the Prussians triumphed over Austria.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Koniggratz</b> (or Battle of<b> Sadowa</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A 1966 essay on this concept describes the \u201cfearful obligation [...] to uphold the pillars of the temple with [a] frail white hand.\u201d<em> Peterson\u2019s Magazine</em> championed this concept, as did a competitor published by Louis Godey.<em> Ruth Hall</em> and other writings of Fanny Fern illustrate the ideals of this concept, which Barbara Welter described in four virtues, including piety, purity, and submissiveness. For ten points, name this 19th century system of moral values that emphasized the woman\u2019s sphere of influence in the home.", "answer": "<b> Cult</b>ure of<b> Domesticity</b> (or<b> cult</b>ure of<b> true womanhood</b> before mentioned; accept word forms)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "After this woman\u2019s husband died, she went to live with Mollie Hay, with whom she may have become romantically involved. This woman invited Eleanor Roosevelt to the Women\u2019s Centennial Congress she organized in 1940. This woman angrily noted how the \u201cThe murderous Sioux is given the right to franchise\u201dwhile women were not. This woman, worked with Emma DeVoe to found the League of Women\u2019s Voters, rose to the head of another organization after the retirement of Susan B. Anthony in 1900. For ten points, name this suffragette who headed NAWSA during the passage of the 19th amendment.", "answer": "Carrie Chapman<b> Catt</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The schism addressed by this council was the subject of the<em> Henotikon</em>, which tried to reconcile the opposing sides. Dioscurus was exiled during this council, which was convoked by the Emperor Marcian. The Oriental Orthodox branch split as a result of this council, which issued a definition that refuted monophysitism and reaffirmed what Pope Leo I explained in a Tome he wrote prior to this council: that Christ had two natures. For ten points, name this 451 church council, held in Asia Minor.", "answer": "Council of<b> Chalcedon</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Like revolutions against Joseph Estrada, this event took place on Epifanio de los Santos Avenue and brought Corazon Aquino to power. For ten points, name this 1986 revolution that overthrew Ferdinand Marcos in the Philippines.", "answer": "<b> People Power Revolution</b> (or<b> EDSA Revolution</b> before \u201cEpifanio de los Santos\u201d is read; or<b> Philippine Revolution of 1986</b> until \u201c1986\u201d is read; accept descriptions of the<b> overthrow</b> of Ferdinand<b> Marcos</b> until his name is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s Park River was buried after a 1936 flood, and it is home to the nation\u2019s oldest publicly funded park, Bushnell Park. According to legend, Samuel Wyllys helped hide a document from Edmund Andros inside a tree here. This city, home to the armory of Samuel Colt and the Charter Oak, also hosted a meeting supported by the Essex Junto that discussed New England secession. Federalists opposed to the War of 1812 met in, for ten points, what city, the capital of Connecticut?", "answer": "<b> Hartford</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After World War II, this agency ran a series of scrap centers, selling surplus bombers to Boy Scout troops and schools. Charles Dawes, Atlee Pomerene, and Eugene Meyer were among the many short-termed leaders of this agency, which, by the time it was closed in 1957, issued $2 billion in aid and loans. For ten points, name this government agency, founded in 1932 under President Hoover and expanded under Jesse Jones during the New Deal, which sought to rebuild the nation\u2019s economic confidence by lending money to banks and businesses.", "answer": "<b> R</b>econstruction<b> F</b>inance<b> C</b>orporation", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader gained power by beating Eric Chu in a 2016 campaign that capitalized on Think Think and Ah Tsai, her cats. This leader, the first of her country with Hakka ancestry, controversially discussed arms sales with Ted Cruz and received a clock from Cruz\u2019s delegation, despite the taboo against giving clocks in Chinese culture. This leader\u2019s 2017 visit to America and call to President-elect Donald Trump sparked fears of Chinese retribution. For ten points, name this President of Taiwan.", "answer": "<b> Tsai</b> Ing-wen", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Elizabeth Noble Shor wrote a popular article about a \u201cfeud\u201d over these objects, as well as a biography of Samuel Williston, who searched for these things with Benjamin Mudge. A man seeking these objects promised to lobby Congress for better treatment for Red Cloud in order to use Sioux land; that man, Othniel Marsh, discovered 24 more of these than Edward Drinker Cope by the end of a 19th century\u201cWar\u201d over them. For ten points, name these objects, many of which were found in another Colorado quarry that, in 1915, Woodrow Wilson proclaimed as Dinosaur National Monument.", "answer": "<b> fossil</b>s (or dinosaur<b> bone</b>s; accept descriptions of the<b> Bone</b> War(s))", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "CIA agent Larry Devlin criticized this action, calling it \u201cmorally wrong,\u201d and argued against Sidney Gottlieb\u2019s plan to do this via poisonous \u201ctoothpaste.\u201d The victim of this event was tortured at the Brouwez House after being held at Camp Hardy in Thysville for over a month. The victim of this event had led his country for nearly three months in 1960 before Belgian-funded secessionists in Katanga forced him out. For ten points, name this January 1961 event that eliminated a political opponent of Mobutu Sese Seko during the Congo Crisis.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> killing</b>, etc.) of Patrice \u00b4Emery<b> Lumumba</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A force led by this man was soundly defeated by the<em> Carolina</em> and other ships under the command of Daniel Patterson. Late in life, this man established a colony in Texas that he named Campeche. Along with his older brother, this man established a base of operations on the island of Barataria. This man\u2019s followers were commended for their performance as gunners and granted a full pardon by Andrew Jackson in 1815. For ten points, name this pirate who assisted the American forces in the Battle of New Orleans.", "answer": "Jean<b> Lafitte</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Article 5 of this document applied the death penalty, replacing life imprisonment, to crimes of poison, flooding, and damage to railways. This proclamation, a response to a crime committed by Marinus van der Lubbe, suspended six Constitutional articles, including protection against unlawful searches and the freedom of the press. Walter Ulbricht went into exile to evade arrest under this proclamation, as did other leaders of the KDP, a Communist party. For ten points, name this February 28, 1933 anti-civil liberty decree, issued by Chancellor Paul von Hindenburg in the wake of an arson on the German Parliament building.", "answer": "<b> Reichstag Fire Decree</b> (or the<b> Decree of the Reich President for the Protection of People and State</b>, or the<b> Reichstagsbrandverordnung</b>; accept equivalents for decree; accept descriptions of a<b> decree</b> passed after the<b> Reichstag fire</b>; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cReichstag decree;\u201d prompt on the Weimar Constitution before \u201cproclamation\u201d is said)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s rule, his country sent an expeditionary force that was mocked as \u201ccannon fodder for the Americans\u201d by Radio Auriverde. This man originally supported the Integralist movement, but cracked down on it after declaring a dictatorship. The system of \u201ccoffee with milk\u201d politics was ended by this man\u2019s rise to power. The Cohen Plan was a non-existent communist plot to overthrow this man\u2019s government, leading him to create an<em> Estado Novo</em>. For ten points, name this 20th century Brazilian dictator.", "answer": "Getulio<b> Vargas</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A manifesto central to this movement was written by the second husband of Jane Fonda. Mark Rudd and other members of this group organized the \u201cTen Days of Resistance\u201d in 1968, including an April 26th strike centered at Columbia that is the largest of its kind in American history. This group advocated\u201cparticipatory democracy\u201d and \u201cuniversally controlled disarmament\u201d in the Port Huron Statement. Weather Underground, or the Weathermen, were originally a faction of, for ten points, what 1960s student activist group?", "answer": "<b> Students for a Democratic Society</b> (or<b> SDS</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man, one of the Chicago Seven arrested at the 1968 DNC, passed away in 2016.", "answer": "Tom<b> Hayden</b> Page 5", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Late Roman examples of these objects were often decorated with detailed reliefs, including one named for Ludovisi showing battles between Romans and Goths. Etruscan examples of these objects featured reclining figures of married couples on couches sculpted in terracotta on top of them. A solid gold one of these shows Akhenaten\u2019s successor holding a crook and flail. For ten points, name these decorative coffins like the one that held the body of King Tutankhamen.", "answer": "<b> sarcophagus</b> (or<b> sarcophagi</b>; prompt on coffins before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Prior to publishing any of his novels, Daniel Defoe fought in this conflict and was pardoned for his role in it. This uprising began with a landing at Lyme Regis and was opposed by forces led by Louis Duras and John Churchill, the future Duke of Marlborough. George Jeffreys, the \u201changing judge,\u201d punished hundreds of members of this uprising with death or labour in the West Indies during the Bloody Assizes. Three years after this uprising failed, its target was replaced by a Dutch stadtholder and his wife. For ten points, name this failed 1685 attempt to overthrow James II, led by James Scott, its namesake Duke.", "answer": "<b> Monmouth</b> Rebellion (accept the<b> West Country</b> Rebellion,<b> Revolt of the West</b>, or similar)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>H.D.\u2019s poem</b><em><b> Trilogy</b></em><b> is a reaction to this event, which is also discussed in a book by Angus Calder about its \u201cMyth.\u201d This event provides the backdrop of Graham Greene\u2019s</b> <b>novel</b><em><b> The</b></em><b> (+)</b> <em><b>End of the Affair</b></em><b>, and Greene\u2019s short story \u201cThe Destructors\u201d concerns a</b> <b>boys\u2019 gang that destroys a house that had survived this event. To escape this event, a group of four characters are sent to live in the house of (*)</b> professor Digory Kirke. While fleeing to the countryside from this event, the Pevensie children discover a gateway to Narnia. For ten points, name this World War Two-era bombing of London.", "answer": "the London<b> Blitz</b> (accept additional information; accept Battle of<b> Britain</b>; accept descriptive answers such as the Nazi German<b> bombing of England</b> until \u201cbombing\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>This man supposedly turned down offers of mercy from Mircea I before his army was destroyed at Rovine by the Wallachians. The Crusade of Nicopolis was called against this</b> <b>man after he initiated the first siege of (+)</b> <b>Constantinople in 1394. This man allegedly</b> <b>killed himself by smashing his head against a metal cage after he was captured. He took power when Milos Obilic assassinated Murad I at (*)</b> Kosovo Field, though he was later defeated at the Battle of Ankara by Tamerlane. For ten points, name this Ottoman sultan whose quick military victories granted him the epithet of Thunderbolt.", "answer": "<b> Bayezid</b> I (or<b> Bayezid</b> the Thunderbolt)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A woman with this married surname was appointed as the first female director of the U.S. mint in 1933. Edmund, a man with this surname, cast the decisive vote that acquitted</b> <b>Andrew Johnson of impeachment charges. (+)</b> <b>Nellie, the aforementioned woman with</b> <b>this married surname, served as the first female governor in Wyoming. A person with this last name supposedly convinced George (*) </b> Washington to adopt a five-pointed star instead of a six-pointed star on a symbol of American independence. For ten points, identify this surname of flag maker Betsy.", "answer": "<b> Ross</b> (accept Nellie Tayloe<b> Ross</b>; accept Edmund<b> Ross</b>; accept Betsy<b> Ross</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Citizens of this country celebrate its re-population after both World Wars with Angam Day. Residents of this country have the world\u2019s highest rate of type 2 diabetes and obesity,</b> <b>and one of its largest employers is a (+)</b> <b>detention center holding people who seek asylum</b> <b>to Australia. The center of this island nation now consists of barren limestone pinnacles, as a result of the depletion of its once-rich (*)</b> phosphate reserves. Yaren is home to the government of, for ten points, what tiny Pacific Island nation, the world\u2019s second least-populous?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Nauru</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A week after this case was decided, Jacob Frohwerk had his similar conviction upheld as well. Because a standard set in this case was not met, Jacob Abrams lost his Supreme</b> <b>Court case eight months later.</b><em><b> Brandenburg v. Ohio</b></em><b> possibly (+)</b> <b>overturned this case,</b> <b>whose central figure worked with Elizabeth Baer to pass out documents with advice like\u201cDo not submit to intimidation,\u201d trying to (*) </b> obstruct the draft. The metaphor of \u201cshouting fire in a crowded theater\u201d was used in, for ten points, what 1919 Supreme Court case concerning the Espionage Act in which Oliver Wendell Holmes outlined the \u201cclear and present danger\u201d test?", "answer": "<b> Schenck</b> v. United States Page 11", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Umayyad Dynasty ruled, for ten points, what early Muslim state in Iberia?", "answer": "Caliphate of<b> C\u00b4ordoba</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this song, performed by Marilyn Monroe for the sitting Commander-in-Chief.", "answer": "<b> Happy Birthday, Mr. President</b> (accept descriptions of \u201c<b>Happy Birthday</b> To You\u201d being sung to<b> J</b>ohn F.<b> Kennedy</b>; accept descriptions of \u201c<b>Happy Birthday</b> To You\u201d being sung by Marilyn <b>Monroe</b> (or Norma Jeane <b>Mortenson</b>); prompt on \u201cHappy Birthday (To You)\u201d alone)  (1) <b>In this state, thee harsh rhetoric of George Prentice helped start nativist riots</b> <b>that came to be known as Bloody Monday. Solomon Sharp was killed during a judicial</b> <b>conflict in this state called the (+) Old Court-New Court Controversy. Braxton Bragg</b> <b>was defeated by Don Carlos Buell at this state\u2019s Battle of Perryville. A Congressman</b> <b>representing this state called for (*) </b> increases in tariffs and infrastructural spending as part of his American System. For ten points, name this state home to Henry Clay and cities like Lexington and Louisville. ANSWER: Commonwealth of<b> Kentucky</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}